Guide to the Akea Brionne Brown photographs, 2016-2018 RL.11693
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Akea Brionne Brown photographs
2016-2018
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Brown, Akea Brionne, 1996-
RL.11693
2.5 Linear Feet 2 boxes 33 prints
These thirty-three color inkjet portraits are from the body of work "Black Picket Fences" by Akea Brionne Brown, and explore the life of middle-class African Americans in the suburbs of Baltimore, Maryland. Taken in part to confront stereotypes of African American neighborhoods and majority black American cities as dangerous and violent, the images chiefly portray family groups and individuals in interiors of homes and in outside environments such as front yards. The majority of the prints measure 19 3/8 x 24 inches. This work received the 2018 ADA Award for Documentarians of Color. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Arrangement
The prints are rranged in original order as assigned by the photographer.
Biographical Note
Akea Brionne Brown's work explores the implications of historical racial and social structures in relation to the development of contemporary black life and identity within America.
She received her BFA from the Maryland Institute College of Art, in the dual degree program of Photography and Integrated Humanistic Studies in 2018. Akea is originally from New Orleans, Louisiana and currently resides in Baltimore, Maryland.
Brown received the 2018 Archive of Documentary Arts Collection Award for Documentarians of Color.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The photographs in this collection were printed with an Epson Stylus Pro 9900 printer, on Epson Archival Premium Luster inkjet paper, using Epson UltraChrome for Stylus Pro ink.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes; any other use requires the photographer's permission.
Provenance
The Akea Brionne Brown photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2018.
Content Description
These thirty-three color inkjet photographs are from the body of work Black Picket Fences by Akea Brionne Brown and explore the lives of middle-class African Americans in the suburbs of Baltimore, Maryland. Taken in part to confront stereotypes of African American neighborhoods and majority black American cities as dangerous and violent, the images chiefly portray family groups and individuals in interiors of homes and in outside environments such as front yards and streets. The majority of the prints measure 19 3/8 x 24 inches. Two are sized slightly smaller at 15 3/4 x 20 3/4 and 15 x 20 1/4 inches.
The prints are accompanied by the artist's statement, in which she writes: "The project manifested through my own personal critique and observation of the suburban landscape as an ideologically 'white space.' I began to consider the importance of representation and exposure in relation to the formation of black identity, the performativity of blackness, and the ways in which the home transforms into a place of familiarity and/or unfamiliarity depending on who enters the space. In turn, this body of work aims to highlight an often overlooked group in contemporary American culture: the black, suburban middle class."
This work received the 2018 ADA Collection Award for Documentarians of Color. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
African American families -- Portraits; African Americans -- Maryland -- Baltimore; African Americans -- Economic conditions -- 21st century; African Americans -- Material culture; African Americans -- Portraits; African Americans -- Social conditions -- 21st century; African Americans -- Social life and customs; Documentary Photography -- Baltimore (Md.); Middle class African Americans -- United States; Middle class -- United States; Suburban African Americans -- Photographs; Color photographs; Digital prints; Inkjet prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Brown, Akea Brionne, 1996-
- Black Picket Fences, Part 1 and Part 2, 2016-2018; 33 prints 1 box; All prints except two measure 19 3/8 x 24 inches. Print 15, "Suburban Kaleidoscope" measures 15 1/2 x 20 3/4 inches. Print 30, "A Family Gathers," measures 15 1/2 x 20 1/4 inches, and has a duplicate image sized 19/3/8 x 24 inches. Titles assigned by the photographer.
  - Jakie, 2017 (Box 1, Image RL.11693-P-0001)
  - Sharon, 2018 (Box 1, Image RL.11693-P-0002)
  - Greg, 2018 (Box 1, Image RL.11693-P-0003)
  - Colette, 2018 (Box 1, Image RL.11693-P-0004)
  - De'Andrea, 2017 (Box 1, Image RL.11693-P-0005)
  - Jesse, 2017 (Box 1, Image RL.11693-P-0006)
  - Gayle, 2018 (Box 1, Image RL.11693-P-0007)
  - Kesha, 2018 (Box 1, Image RL.11693-P-0008)
  - David, 2018 (Box 1, Image RL.11693-P-0009)
  - Kyle, 2017 (Box 1, Image RL.11693-P-0010)
  - Bill, 2017 (Box 1, Image RL.11693-P-0011)
  - Zoe, 2017 (Box 1, Image RL.11693-P-0012)
  - La'Dre, 2018 (Box 1, Image RL.11693-P-0013)
  - Distant fairytale, 2018 (Box 1, Image RL.11693-P-0014)
  - Suburban kaleidoscope, 2018 (Box 1, Image RL.11693-P-0015)
  - Morning motivation, 2018 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0016)
  - The dining room, 2018 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0017)
  - Come with me, 2016 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0018)
  - Untitled (Hair tie), 2016 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0019)
  - Garage shoe collection, 2018 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0020)
  - In the name of Allah, 2018 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0021)
  - Tupac, 2016 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0022)
  - Bathtime, 2018 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0023)
  - Untitled (Conversation), 2018 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0024)
  - Brown Sugar, 2018 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0025)
  - Stevie, 2018 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0026)
  - Coffee table portraits, 2017 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0027)
  - Open door, 2016 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0028)
  - Accolades, 2017 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0029)
  - A family gathers (smaller format), 2016 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0030)
  - Porch sittin', 2018 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0031)
  - House at dusk, 2018 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0032)
  - A family gathers (larger format), 2016 (Box 2, Image RL.11693-P-0033)